<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<rss type="dict">
	<channel type="list">
		<title>Yang Shun's CS3216 Blog</title>
		<description>Hi I'm Yang Shun. This is my blog. I build cool stuff.</description>
		<link>http://yangshun.im/cs3216/#/</link>
		<item type="dict">
			<pubDate type="str">2014-01-02</pubDate>
			<description type="str">When going for GEMs, two questions inevitably come to mind: which GEM should I go for, and how much should I bid for it? These questions will have a significant impact on your semester ahead as well as your remaining time in NUS. 

At [**Corspedia**](http://www.corspedia.com), we strive to ensure that your CORS points are spent wisely - with tips to sieve out gems amongst the GEMs. We unveil 3 key messages to help you manage your points wisely. 

#### Choose Your GEMs Wisely ####

Two areas to consider while choosing GEMs are: your interest &amp; strength in the topic, and the cost of the GEMs. 

It is important to take GEMs that you are interested in, and naturally you can excel in. If the GEMs you prefer are popular, expect to pay up to an additional 1200* points (see below). We have listed the 3 most ‘expensive’ GEMs with bidding data over the past 2 years.

We will be coming up with the entire list of GEMs and their ‘cost’ shortly.

**GEM2023 - Primary Health Care** (Not offered in AY13/14 Semester 2)  
*Average Winning Bid: 1460*  
The minimum winning bids for this module exceed 1400! That’s at least 3-4 semesters worth of general account points - if you want to take this module, start saving now!

**GEM1900 - Public Health in Action**  
*Average Winning Bid: 1274*  
A new course offered since the second semester of AY12/13, this module has been looking a minimum winning bid of at least 500. We expect the demand for this module to carry through to the coming semester. 

**GEM1023 - Living Amidst Outbreaks**  
*Average Winning Bid: 1130*  
The highly popular GEM only offered in semester 2- make sure you have at least 800 points before you decide to take it! 


#### Bid early ####

Bidding early for GEMs is important - the winning bid for a GEM in round 3 most cost up to more than 1800 points more! (Living Admist Outbreaks).

The uncertainty of the quota in later rounds, and increased demand (for students who want to overload) for these slots would usually indicate a significantly higher winning bid.

This quota in rounds 3A and 3B, especially for popular GEMs, comes from students who dropped the module, as the module is usually usually full after round 2A. 

![stats](img/stats.png)

The diagram above shows the additional points (in red) per module for a winning bid in later rounds. Comparing this to the blue base, which is the winning bid for each GEM in round 2A, the additional points required can be significant! 

#### Choosing Between Multiple GEMs ####

Do you have multiple GEMs which you can’t decide to go for? One strategy to take is to bid for all of the GEMs that you are interested in taking in round 2A. Once you have made up your mind, you can drop the rest at a penalty cost of 50%.

For example, if you cannot decide between GEM1023 (Living Amidst Outbreaks) and GEM2005 (Introduction to Urban Planning), bid for them in round 2A, at an average cost of 1100 and 700 points respectively. 

Once you have decided on one, for example, GEM2005, you can drop GEM1023 for a refund of 550 points. The entire process costs 1250 points, as opposed to bidding for GEM2005 in round 3 which would have costed 2100 points. 

Keep in mind that to do this, you will need to have sufficient module points to place winning bids for both modules, as well as not exceed the MC limit for bidding in round 2A (23 MCs) - [See Workload Policy](http://www.nus.edu.sg/cors/policies.html).

In addition, this strategy will only work for popular modules when the round 3 bids are highly competitive, and saving points are not guaranteed. *(Of course, the alternative is to select a module early on before round 2A)*

Do remember to bid wisely and not bid unnecessarily for modules you do not want, for you are depriving another NUS student of their allocated slot. 

Stay tuned for other features - bid on!

*Corspedia will not be responsible for any unsuccessful attempts to bid for modules in the suggested strategies and hope that readers are fully aware of the risks involved.*

*GEMs selected for the study must have a class enrolment greater than 20. They must also not be any part of another core curriculum, where students use P points to bid for them. All points are based on the winning bids of successful bidders during the period of AY2012/AY2013 and AY2013/AY2014.*</description>
			<title type="str">Dummies Guide to Bidding for NUS GEMs</title>
			<link type="str">http://yangshun.im/cs3216/#/dummies-guide-to-bidding-for-nus-gems</link>
			<guid type="str">dummies-guide-to-bidding-for-nus-gems</guid>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
